Hello, this is an attempt to summarize Tatsuno's approach to teaching English in elementary school.
こんにちは。これは、たつの市の小学校における 英語教育のアプローチのまとめです。
The information is based on my experience over the past year in the position of an ALT
この情報は、ALTの立場で過ごした過去1年間の経験と、
and my conversations with other ALT's, teachers, members of the board of education and parents.
他のALT、学校教員、教育委員会、そして 保護者との会話に基づいています。
Although I'll be speaking in English, the target audience includes all of them and anyone else with an interest in the subject.
私は英語で話しますが、対象者はこのテーマに関心のあるすべての人たちです。
Any leaking opinions are mine alone.
ここに含まれている意見は、私自身のものです。
First of all, I should discuss Tatsuno's approach to teaching English in relation to my understanding of how some other cities handle it.
まず第一に、私は他のいくつかの市が英語教育をどのように取り組んでいるかという私自身の理解と関連して、たつの市の英語教育のアプローチについて議論すべきです。
Each city has its own overall approach to teaching English in elementary school.
各都市の小学校での英語教育に対する全体的なアプローチはそれぞれである。
Some cities have English specialists who are responsible for teaching English to third through sixth grades.
一部の市では、英語の専門家が3年生から6年生までの英語を担当しています。
Some cities have any combination of home room teachers, English specialists or
一部の市では、担任の先生、英語専門家、または中学校の英語教師
English teachers from junior high schools come to teaching English in elementary schools.
が組み合わせて小学校で英語の指導を行います。
This depends on location number of students and availability of staff.
立地条件や生徒数、スタッフの有無によって異なります。
Some cities hire enough ALTs to join each class each week. Other cities only hire enough ALTs to join each class once or twice a month.
ある都市では、毎週各クラスに参加できるだけのALTを雇っている。 また、月に１、２回しかALTを雇わない都市もある。
There are different ALT agencies for cities to choose from.
ALTの派遣会社は都市によって異なります。
Each agency has its own hiring standards employment benefits and training procedures
それぞれのALT派遣会社には、独自の採用基準 雇用手当や研修の方法など
But generally the ALT position is considered a temporary position.
しかし、一般的にALTのポジションは臨時職とみなされます。
This inevitably has some effect on how seriously their role is taken. And I'll talk more about this very complicated aspect later.
これは必然的に、彼らの役割がどの程度真剣に受け止められているかに影響します。 この非常に複雑な側面については、後で詳しくお話しします。
Different cities have different working relationships with their ALT agencies.
都市によってALTとの関係は異なる。
Although the English curriculum is determined by the prefecture cities that rely more heavily on ALTs may also
英語のカリキュラムは都道府県が決めるが ALTへの依存度が高い都市では、ALTとの関係も異なる。
rely on their respective agencies for providing lesson plans and teacher training.
授業計画や教員研修の提供については、それぞれの機関に依存している。
Some cities also ask ALTs to take on a more active role in the classroom than others.
都市によっては、ALTに他の都市よりも積極的に授業に参加するよう求めているところもある。 また、ALTに授業での積極的な役割を求める都市もある。
There are even cities that are considering foregoing the ALT position all together and hiring native English speakers to teach English lessons assisted by the home room teachers.
ALTの職を全面的に放棄し ALTの職をすべて放棄し、英語のネイティブ・スピーカーを雇うことを検討している都市もある。 を雇い、ホームルーム教師の補助のもと英語の授業を行うことを検討している市もある。
As for Tatsuno...
たつの市はというと
The city of Tatsuno covers a large area with schools of all sizes.
たつの市の面積は広く、大小さまざまな学校がある。
So the teaching situations vary quite a bit. Generally, third and fourth grade homeroom teachers lead the lessons once a week with the ALT assisting each time.
そのため、指導状況もさまざまだ。 一般的には、3年生と4年生の担任が授業を担当し、週に1回ALTが補助に入る。 週1回、ALTがアシスタントをします。
Fifth and sixth grade classes have English lessons twice a week the first lesson is taught either by an English specialist
5年生と6年生のクラスでは英語の授業があります。 週2回、最初の授業は英語の専門家が担当します。
or by the homeroom teacher alone. The second is taught by the same person assisted by an ALT.
または担任教師が単独で行う。 2回目の授業は、同じ教師がALTの助けを借りて行います。
The agency that trains and provides ALTs for Tatsuno also facilitates training sessions for teachers.
たつの市にALTを養成・派遣している機関は、教師向けの研修も行っている。 また、教師向けの研修も行っている。
These sessions are voluntary for homeroom teachers.
担任の先生を対象にした自主的なものです。
However, English specialists are required to attend these sessions periodically as well as other training sessions
しかし、英語のスペシャリストは、定期的にこのセッションに参加することが義務付けられています。 このような研修は、担任教師が任意で参加するものです。
facilitated by the city and the prefecture.
市と県が推進。
I think this is a balanced and relatively progressive approach...in my opinion.
これはバランスの取れた、比較的進歩的なアプローチだと...私は思います。
Because every student can interact with a native English speaker at least once a week
すべての生徒が 少なくとも週に一度はネイティブスピーカーと
Homeroom teachers in third and fourth grade make great English speaking role models for their students.
小学3年生と4年生の担任の教師は 年生の担任教師は、英語を話す生徒の模範となる。
I believe fifth and sixth grade in some schools, too.
学校によっては5,6年生もそうだと思います。
All the students get some English instruction exclusively with a Japanese teacher.
全生徒が日本人の先生と 日本人の先生と一緒です。
Many students need certain things explained thoroughly as well as opportunities to ask questions without the pressure of being
多くの生徒が、特定の事柄を徹底的に説明する必要があります。 質問する機会が必要です。 というプレッシャーを感じずに
expected to use language  they're not comfortable with yet. And then they have a second lesson to practice what they've learned.
を使うことを期待される。 そして、2回目のレッスンで学んだことを練習するのです。
This has the potential to be very productive and fun.
これは非常に生産的で楽しいものになる可能性がある。
And also it is really important to give the students confidence and enthusiasm
また、生徒たちに自信と熱意を与えることも重要だ。
before they enter the junior high school English program.
中学校の英語コースに入る前に。
So with all this being said, it was done a bit differently last year and it will be done a bit differently next year as
というわけで、昨年は少し違った形で行われた。 昨年は少し違った形で行われた。
Tatsuno pushes to unify the curriculum between elementary and junior high school.
たつの市は小学校と中学校のカリキュラムの統一を推進している。
So even within the city of Tatsuno, it does depend on the school and
つまり、たつの市内であっても、学校によって、また
there are many factors. Among the most significant are the number of classes
様々な要因がある。その中でも クラス数
Each school has a different number of classes in each grade and all together.
学校によってクラス数は違います。 学校によってクラス数が異なる。
For large schools planning lessons may be delegated.
大規模な学校では、授業の計画を委任することもあります。
I worked at a large school this year with either five or six classes in each grade.
私は今年、大規模校で働いた。 各学年5クラスか6クラスでした。
For third and fourth grades. It would be impractical to me with each of twelve homeroom tachers
3年生と4年生の場合 それは 12人の担任を持つのは非現実的だ。
to discuss what to do in class. Instead one of the homeroom teachers in each grade
授業で何をするかを話し合うのは現実的ではありません。 代わりに各学年の担任の一人が
made the lesson plan for all teachers in that grade. This is how we kept all classes on the same page.
代わりに各学年の担任の一人が、その学年の教師全員のために授業計画を立てた。 こうして、すべてのクラスが同じページを見られるようにしたのです。
However, there are a few problems built into this approach.
しかし、この方法にはいくつかの問題がある。
Most teachers follow a lesson plan written by someone else.
ほとんどの教師は、誰かが書いたレッスンプランに従っている。
The teacher who actually makes the lesson plan with the ALT knows exactly what to do and when. Other teachers receive a copy of the lesson plan
実際にALTとレッスンプランを立てる教師は は、いつ何をすべきかを正確に把握しています。 他の教師は授業計画のコピーを受け取る
but may not understand exactly how to proceed or where they're needed to explain or help demonstrate.
しかし、どのように授業を進めればよいのか、どこで説明 説明したり、実演を手伝ったりする必要がある。
Even if it is made clear, there may be several days before the plan is used in the classroom.
たとえそれが明確であったとしても、その計画が教室で使われるまでに数日 を理解できないかもしれない。
It's also easy to overlook things that need to be prepared before class.
また また、授業前に準備しなければならないことを見落としがちである。
It is difficult to refine the lesson plan because it's already written.
レッスンプランが既に書かれているため、練り直すのが難しい。
The ALT gains valuable experience each time they teach the lesson and may find something that needs more clarification
ALTは授業をするたびに貴重な経験を積むことができます。
or a more fun way to do something and there isn't often an opportunity to communicate this with the next teacher or teachers.
るかもしれない。 それを次の先生や教師に伝える機会はあまりありません。 を次の教師に伝える機会がない。
But doing things off-script may create confusion.
しかし、台本にないことをするのは混乱を生むかもしれない。
The scheduling and rescheduling of lessons can get very chaotic.
レッスンのスケジューリングやリスケジューリングは非常に混乱します。
The schedule in elementary school can be very unpredictable. Even more so with more classes.
小学校でのスケジュールは予測不可能です。 クラスが増えればなおさらです。
Different classes in the same grade are often at different points in the curriculum.
同じ学年でもクラスが違えば 同じ学年でもクラスが違えば、カリキュラムも違ってくる。
This makes it a bit hard to keep track of what each class needs to be doing.
このため、各クラスが何をすべきかを把握するのは少し難しい。 各クラスが何をすべきかを把握するのは少し難しい。
There are several smaller schools in Tatsuno which face a different set of challenges.
たつの市にはいくつかの小規模校がある。 辰野には小規模校がいくつかあり、それぞれ異なる課題を抱えている。
The ALT may only be at the school one or two days a week.
ALTは週に1日か2日しか学校にいないかもしれない。
The fewer days an ALT is at a particular school, the fewer opportunities ther are
ALTが特定の学校にいる日数が少なければ少ないほど
to build relationships with students or discuss classes and teaching ideas with other teachers.
生徒と関係を築いたり 生徒と関係を築いたり、他の教師と授業や指導のアイデアについて話し合ったりする機会が少なくなる。
There may be no opportunity to discuss lesson plans. It's usually preferable to plan classes well ahead.
授業計画について話し合う機会はないかもしれない。 通常、授業は余裕を持って計画することが望ましい。
However, if the only day to discuss a class is the day of class
しかし、授業について話し合う日が授業当日しかない場合
the ALT barely has an opportunity to ask questions discuss ideas for activities or even suggest improvements.
ALTはほとんど質問をする機会がない。 活動のアイデアを話し合ったり、改善点を提案したりする機会すらない。
And the ability to reschedule lessons is very limited.
また、レッスンのスケジュールを変更することもできません。
It's impossible to reschedule a lesson for a different day of the same week because the ALT is only at that particular school one day a week.
同じ週の別の日にレッスンを振り替えることは不可能です。 ALTは週に1日しかその学校にいないので、同じ週の別の日に授業を変更することは不可能です。 を変更することは不可能です。
One or two days a week. This means there may be large gaps between lessons more often
週に1日か2日です。 つまり、授業と授業の間が大きく空くことが多くなります。
But beyond just the number of classes, it also depends on the class size.
しかし、授業数だけではありません、 授業数だけでなく、クラスの規模にもよります。
This is always an issue in education and especially I think with
これは教育において常に問題となることであり、特に次のようなことが挙げられると思う。
second language lessons and classes.
第二外国語の授業やクラスでは特にそうだと思います。
In general classes for learning a foreign language need to be large enough to create a fun atmosphere and
一般的に外国語を学ぶクラスは 楽しい雰囲気を作るには、十分な人数が必要である。
limit the amount of pressure on each individual student. They also need to be large enough to allow pair conversation or group work.
また、生徒一人一人にプレッシャーがかからないような規模でなければならない。 また、ペアでの会話やグループワークができるような大きさも必要です。
However, they should be small enough that the overall noise doesn't drown out each person speaking and the teacher is able to give each student attention and feedback.
しかし、全体の雑音が 全体的な雑音にかき消されることなく、一人一人が話すことができる。 教師は生徒一人一人に注意を払い、フィードバックを与えることができる。
Most classes in public schools are 30 to 35 students.
公立学校のほとんどのクラスは30人から35人です。
This is certainly large enough to create a fun low-pressure atmosphere. So much so that classes can become very difficult to manage.
これは確かに、楽しくプレッシャーの少ない雰囲気を作るには十分な人数だ。 そのため、クラスの運営が非常に難しくなることもある。
Some challenges that also exist in smaller classes are compounded in larger classes.
少人数クラスにも存在するいくつかの課題は 少人数のクラスにもある課題が、大人数のクラスではさらに深刻になります。
Some students demand attention and will disrupt the lesson to get it.
注意を引くことを要求し、そのために授業を妨害する生徒がいる。 る生徒もいる。
Others who also need attention but are less vocal may feel neglected or lose interest.
また、注意が必要だが、あまり声を出さない生徒もいる。 を無視されたと感じたり、興味を失ったりするかもしれません。
While these points are also true in smaller classes, in larger classes
これらの点は、少人数のクラスでも当てはまるが、大人数のクラスでは
it becomes far more pronounced when students who cry out for attention have to either combine forces or compete with each other
生徒が注意を を競い合わなければならない。 力を合わせるか、競い合うかしなければならない。
Likewise, the large number of students who are unwilling to ask for help almost guarantees that
同様に、助けを求めようとしない生徒が多いことは 助けを求めようとしない生徒が多いことは、ほぼ確実である。
The teacher will be unable to engage each one of them individually to give them the attention they need.
教師は生徒一人一人に必要な注意を払うことができない。 を一人一人に与えることができない。
But beyond just those who cry out for attention and those who sort of want to blend in
しかし その中に溶け込もうとする
students generally respond better when they are engaged as individuals and not as such a large group.
生徒たちは一般的に、そのような集団としてではなく としてではなく、一個人として関わっているときに、生徒たちはよりよい反応を示すのです。
In short, it's too difficult to stand out from the crowd and too easy to disappear into it.
要するに、群衆の中で目立つことはあまりにも難しく 集団の中に消えてしまうのは簡単すぎる。
The approach that makes large classes manageable when teaching other subjects doesn't work well for English lessons.
他の教科を教えるときに、大人数のクラスを管理しやすくするアプローチは 英語の授業ではうまくいかない。
A teacher-centered classroom where students face forward and speak only to the teacher only when called upon
教師中心の教室では、生徒は前を向き 生徒が前を向き、呼ばれた時だけ先生に話しかける。
may be the way to create a manageable classroom setting in situations where the students are expected to
をすることが、管理しやすい教室環境を作る方法かもしれない。 を期待される状況において、管理しやすい教室環境を作り出す方法かもしれない。
solve problems and retain information.
問題を解決し、情報を保持する。
However, classes that focus on communication cannot be expected to operate effectively in this way.
しかし、コミュニケーション このように効果的な運用は期待できない。
There is great potential for developing a student-centered approach.
生徒中心のアプローチを発展させる大きな可能性がある。
So, even within any school it depends on the grade because
どの学校であっても、学年によって異なるからです。
the curriculum is handled... the approach the teaching is handled differently depending on the grade.
カリキュラムの扱い方...授業の進め方...。 学年によって異なるからです。
In third and fourth grade classes, they are considered an activity.
3年生と4年生のクラスでは 活動として考えられている。
Classes in these grades are only taught once a week. The homeroom teacher is considered T1 and leads the lesson.
これらの学年の授業は週1回のみです。 担任の教師はT1とみなされ、授業を指導する。
The ALT follows their lead as T2 and the students are not graded.
ALTはT2として彼らの指導に従います。 生徒の成績はつけません。
In fifth and sixth grade classes,
5年生と6年生のクラスで
they are considered a subject. They're taught twice a week.
教科として扱われる。週2回の授業です。
And again one is led either by the homeroom teacher or an English specialist as T1 without the ALT.
また、担任の先生か、英語の専門家が指導します。 または英語の専門家が担当します。
The other lesson has the teacher assisted by the ALT as T2.
もう1つの授業はT2としてALTがアシストします。
Students are required to take listening and conversation tests.
リスニングと会話のテストがあります。
Students' performance in English class is reflected on their report card.
英語の成績は成績表に反映されます。
This may be the most complicated
これが一番複雑かもしれない。
aspect of this whole presentation.
このプレゼンテーションの中で最も複雑な点かもしれない。
It depends on the homeroom teacher the JTE or English specialist the ALT and all of their working relationships.
担任の先生やJTE、英語のスペシャリスト、ALT、そして彼らの仕事上の関係全てに左右されます。 ALT、そしてそのすべての人間関係によって決まります。
And before before I get into this I just want to
そして、本題に入る前に言っておきたいことがある。
emphasize how hard all of these teachers are working at their extremely complicated jobs...
先生方がいかに大変な仕事をこなし 非常に複雑な仕事であることを強調しておきたい。
extremely complicated and difficult jobs and I hope my comments are interpreted with the utmost respect
非常に複雑で困難な仕事であり 私のコメントが最大限の敬意をもって解釈されることを願っています。
for the work they all do.
私のコメントが、彼らの仕事に対して最大限の敬意をもって解釈されることを願っている。
So with that being said, it does depend on the homeroom teacher.
担任の先生にもよりますが。
Some homeroom teachers are more proficient in English than others and they'll tell you this themselves.
担任によっては英語が堪能な教師もいる。 担任によっては英語が堪能な先生もいます。
Some homeroom teachers have enough confidence in their English proficiency.
担任の中には自分の英語力に 英語力に自信のある担任もいます。
Many people, even teachers, hide their English proficiency.
教師であっても英語力を隠している人は多い。
They may understand English well enough to lead an English lesson
英会話レッスンを指導できるくらいには英語が理解できるかもしれない
but that doesn't mean they have enough confidence
しかし、それが自信につながるとは限らない。
in their own ability to feel comfortable leading an English lesson.
しかし、それは英会話レッスンの指導に自信があるということではありません。
Some homeroom teachers would just rather leave it to the pros
プロに任せたい担任もいる
as it were.
というように。
Proficient in English or not, some would simply rather leave the English instruction to a native speaker or at least someone who specializes in it.
英語が堪能であろうとなかろうと、英語の指導は 英語の指導をネイティブ・スピーカーに任せたい。 英語はネイティブスピーカーか、少なくともそれを専門とする人に任せたいと思う人もいる。
This is how other subjects like music and calligraphy are handled.
音楽や書道など他の教科もこのように扱われている。
And again, homeroom teachers already handle an enormous load.
そしてまた、担任の教師はすでに膨大な量の仕事をこなしている。
But then many teachers are quite confident and enthusiastic about teaching English.
しかし、多くの教師は英語教育に自信があり 英語教育に熱意を持っている。
Early on, I made the mistake of assuming that everyone would be happy if I took on as much of
最初の頃、私は、私がこの仕事を引き受ければ、みんなが喜んでくれると思い込んでいた。 を引き受ければ皆が喜ぶと思い込んでしまった。
the responsibility for teaching English lessons as possible
英会話レッスンの責任を出来るだけ引き受ければ、皆が喜ぶと思ったのが間違いだった。
In reality, I was just depriving those homeroom teachers of an opportunity to set a good example for their students by taking a more active role in English lessons themselves.
現実には、私は担任の先生たちから、良い手本を示す機会を奪っていただけだった。 生徒の手本となる機会を奪っていたのだ。 担任の先生方が英語の授業に積極的に参加することで、生徒の手本となる機会を奪っていたのです。
It also, of course, depends on the ALT.
もちろん、ALTにもよります。
Each ALT has their own idea of what their role is and should be.
ALTには、それぞれの役割とあるべき姿がある。
Some ALTs take their role as educators more seriously than the term assistant language teacher recognizes.
ALTの中には、教育者としての自分の役割を、外国語指導助手という言葉以上に重 ALTの中には、教育者としての役割をより真剣に受け止めている人もいます。
They want to do anything they can to improve their students' communication skills and be a positive influence on their lives.
生徒のコミュニケーション能力を向上させ
Some ALTs are happy to take on a temporary position sharing their language and culture with children for a year or two
ALTの中には、一時的な雇用を喜んで引き受ける人もいる。 ALTの中には、1～2年の間、子どもたちと言語や文化を共有する臨時の職を喜んで引き受ける人もいる。
while they enjoy the experience of learning a bit about language and culture of a foreign country themselves.
の言語や文化を学ぶ経験を楽しむ。 その一方で、自分自身も外国の言語や文化を学ぶという経験を楽しむのである。
Of course, either and everything in between is perfectly fine
もちろん、どちらでもいいし、その中間でもいい。
but each ALT must deal with the previous
しかし、それぞれのALTは前のALTに対応しなければならない。
experiences and expectations of staff members who have worked with other ALTs.
の経験と期待に対応しなければならない。 他のALTと働いたことのあるスタッフの経験や期待に対応しなければならない。
ALTs may face unreasonable
ALTは理不尽なことに直面するかもしれない。
expectations of their ability to lead engaging and productive lessons in such a challenging situation.
このような困難な状況において、魅力的で生産的な授業を指導する能力に対する
Assuming that they should be expected to lead the lesson in the first place.
そもそもレッスンをリードすることを期待されるべきだと仮定して。
But facing unreasonably low expectations presents a different struggle.
しかし、不当に低い期待に応えることは 別の葛藤がある。
It may be difficult to get their ideas and methods put into practice or even try things to find out
彼らのアイデアや方法を実践させるのは難しいかもしれない。 実践することが難しいかもしれない。
what works, what doesn't doesn't work and why.
何がうまくいき、何がうまくいかないのか、そしてその理由は何なのか。
They may only be asked to flash cards and model pronunciation a few times during class.
授業中に数回、フラッシュカードや発音の模範を 発音を練習するのは授業中数回だけです。
The ALT may spend a lot of the class time just waiting for their cue.
ALTは、授業の多くの時間を、自分の合図を待つことに費やすかもしれません。 出番を待つだけです。
It's sometimes difficult to stay engaged in the lessons themselves.
授業そのものに 授業に集中することが難しい。
With the homeroom teacher and JTE responsible for setting the pace and flow of the lesson,
担任の先生とJTEは、授業のペースや流れを作る責任を負っています。 担任とJTEが授業のペースと流れを決める、
they will naturally end up modeling some of the language themselves.
を、自然にモデル化することになる。 を自らモデル化することになる。
Even more so in fifth and sixth grade classes because for one lesson each week there is no ALT.
5年生や6年生のクラスではなおさらだ。 毎週1レッスン、ALTがいないからです。
It just comes naturally to model the language themselves.
自分たちの言葉を手本にするのは、ごく自然なことです。
Although it may be appreciated and encouraged,
評価され、奨励されるかもしれないが、
it's not expected that the ALT will develop a meaningful relationship with the students.
ALTが生徒と有意義な関係を築くことは期待されていない。 生徒と有意義な関係を築くことは期待できない。
Even if an ALT sticks with the job for more than a year, they're often reassigned to other schools.
たとえALTが1年以上勤め続けても 1年以上勤めたとしても、他の学校に配置転換されることが多い。
Homeroom teachers who spend all day every day with their students know their students very well.
毎日一日中生徒と一緒にいる担任教師は、生徒のことをよく知っている。 生徒のことをよく知っている。
And even JTEs who spend two hours a week for a number of years
また、週に2時間を何年も過ごすJTEでさえ、生徒のことをよく知っている。
can at least be expected to remember all their student's names.
少なくとも、生徒の名前をすべて覚えることはできるだろう。
This is not so for ALTs who spend 45 minutes a week with each class of 30 plus students for one year...
しかし、週に45分、30人以上の生徒の授業を受け持つALTはそうではない。 1クラス30人以上の生徒と1年間...
even in classes where the students wear name tags.
生徒が名札をつけているクラスでさえも。
It may be difficult to find experienced ALTs or to keep those that gain experience.
経験豊富なALTを見つけるのは難しいかもしれません。
Teaching English as a second language to large groups of small children in mixed level classes
第二言語として英語を教える 少人数の子どもたちを対象とした 教える。
is probably the most challenging EFL teaching situation there is.
は、おそらく最も困難な EFLを教えるのは、おそらく最も難しい状況です。
Although the job is certainly available to experienced teachers and it's preferable to sign ALTs who have gained experience,
この仕事は確かに経験豊富な 経験を積んだALTと契約することが望ましい。 経験を積んだALTが望ましい、
many of those people opt for more lucrative and less strenuous job opportunities.
そのような人々の多くは、より有利で、より激務でない仕事を選ぶ。 を選ぶ人が多い。
Experience beyond teaching materials and methodology is important too.
教材や方法論以外の経験 教材や方法論以外の経験も重要です。
The term culture shock refers to the difficulty of getting used to doing and thinking about things differently.
カルチャーショックという言葉は カルチャーショックとは、異なるやり方や考え方に慣れることの難しさを指す。
Something more akin to culture fatigue starts to set in after a few years of getting used to a culture that doesn't seem to be getting used to you.
文化疲労に似たものが始まる。 馴染めない文化に慣れてくると、文化疲労に似たものが出てくる。
Many ALTs are just serious enough about their work and just experienced enough working in the field
多くのALTは、自分の仕事に対して真剣であり 現場で働くのに十分な経験を積んでいる。
that they become frustrated with the lack of influence that they have on improving their own situation and the circumstances for their students.
自分たちの状況を改善する影響力のなさに苛立ちを覚える。 苛立つようになる。
It is difficult to stay optimistic when you always feel like the new guy or a guest at your workplace.
楽観的でいることは難しい。 常に新人のように、あるいは職場のお客さんのように感じているようでは、楽観的でいることは難しい。
Again, some people are fine with the temporary ALT position
繰り返しになるが、一時的なALTポジションでも構わないという人もいる
but others hope to eventually gain a real sense of job security and a sense that they're an experienced and valued part of a team.
を得ることを望む人もいる。 経験豊富で、チームの一員として評価されることを望む人もいる。
Okay, and it also depends on the working relationship between all the teaching staff...
そうですね。 教職員の関係にもよりますが...
homeroom teachers, JTEs and ALTs
担任、JTE、ALT
Due to all the variables discussed thus far ALTs must be very flexible
これまで述べてきたような変数のために ALTは非常に柔軟でなければならない。
in their approach to teaching English.
英語教育へのアプローチにおいてである。
When an English specialist is leading the lesson,
英語の専門家がレッスンを指導する場合、
even experienced ALTs have to be comfortable following their lead.
経験豊富なALTであっても、そのリードに従わなければならない。
The ALT may have many suggestions regarding
ALTは次のようなことを提案する。
the curriculum, materials or pedagogy but, ultimately,
カリキュラム、教材、教育法に関して、ALTは多くの提案をすることができる、
it's the JTE who bears responsibility for what the students cover.
しかし、最終的には、生徒が何を学ぶかについて責任を負うのはJTEなのです。
The JTE teaches another entire lesson solo each week
JTEは毎週、別のレッスン全体をソロで教えている。
so they will have a better idea of where those specific students are and how the class needs to be managed.
そうすれば、特定の生徒がどこにいて を把握することができる。
When the homeroom teacher leads the class,
担任がクラスをリードするとき、
ALTs need to be comfortable following the lead of the homeroom teacher.
ALTは担任のリードに従うことに抵抗がない。
But, I believe they also need to be comfortable leading the lessons themselves if necessary.
しかし、必要であれば、自ら授業をリードすることも必要だと思います。 必要であれば、自ら授業をリードすることも必要だと思います。
Homeroom teachers may be absent unexpectedly.
担任が突然欠席することがあります。
Sometimes homeroom teachers get sick and the ALT will already be more prepared than the substitute teacher.
担任の先生が病気になることもあります。 担任が病気になることもあります。
English classes could be rescheduled, but consistent practice is far better
英語の授業は振り替えが可能です、 しかし、一貫した練習の方がはるかに良い。
Homeroom teachers may have to deal with emergencies.
担任は緊急事態に対処しなければならないかもしれません。
Sometimes homeroom teachers have to deal with emergency situations involving students
担任が緊急事態に対処しなければならないこともあります。 生徒の緊急事態に対処しなければならない。
and you never know when they will happen or how long they'll take to resolve.
いつ起こるかわからないし いつ起こるかわからない。
Not all homeroom teachers approach English lessons with the same enthusiasm.
すべての担任が同じ熱意で英語の授業に取り組んでいるわけではない。 すべての担任が同じ熱意を持って英語の授業に取り組むわけではありません。
The concern has been raised that some homeroom teachers are less interested in doing their job where teaching English is concerned.
担任教師の中には、英語を教えることにあまり興味を示さない人もいるようです。
But consider the fact that teaching English is not a part of the homeroom teacher's job in every city.
しかし、英語を教えることは どの都市でも担任の仕事の一部ではないのです。
And they also trade responsibility for it depending on the school.
また、学校によって 学校によっては、担任を交換することもある。
Many cities and schools have English specialists teaching third and fourth grade and
多くの都市や学校では、英語の専門家を置いている。 いる都市や学校が多い。
Tatsuno could opt for this approach, but it's a step backward in my opinion.
たつの市はこの方法を選ぶこともできる、 しかし、それは一歩後退だと私は思う。
Some homeroom teachers simply need more assistance than others.
担任の先生によっては、他の先生よりもサポートが必要な場合もあります。
If a teacher is willing to lead the class, they certainly should;
教師がクラスをリードする気があるなら、そうすべきだ；
They may model imperfect pronunciation or make mistakes that a native speaker wouldn't but it's important for students to have a real
不完全な発音を見本にしたり ネイティブスピーカーがしないような間違いをすることもある。 しかし、生徒にとって重要なのは、生徒が本当の
English-speaking Japanese role model they can look up to.
しかし、生徒にとって、英語を話す日本人を手本にすることは大切なことです。
However, if a teacher is only going to demonstrate unwillingness to try
しかし、もし教師が やる気がない。
by saying things like I don't speak English out loud during the lesson, it's better to let someone else lead.
というようなことをレッスン中に大声で言うのであれば を大声で言うような教師は、他の人にリードしてもらった方がいい。
The ALT gains experience each time they teach the same lesson
ALTは同じレッスンをするたびに経験を積んでいく。
Teaching a lesson once gives them an opportunity to make adjustments so that it's smoother, more productive
一度でもレッスンを教えることで よりスムーズで生産的な授業ができるように調整することができる。
and more fun for subsequent classes. Without this insight each class has to follow the rough draft.
次の授業がより楽しくなる。 このような洞察がなければ、毎回の授業は下書きに従わなければならない。
This is a benefit that the English specialists have
これは英語のスペシャリストが持っている利点である。
in fifth and sixth grades
小学5年生と6年生では
that could and should be applied to all classes if possible.
このようなことは、可能であれば全クラスに適用されるべきである。
And finally, this is the direction English instruction will eventually need to move anyway.
そして最後に、これは英語 の指導は、いずれにせよ、この方向に進む必要がある。
It's more efficient for the one person who's going to be present during each lesson to prepare for the lesson
その方が効率的です。 そのため、このような指導の方向性は、最終的には必要なことだと思います。
rather than each homeroom teacher being more or less prepared and all of them proceeding in different ways
各担任が多かれ少なかれ準備をし をする方が効率的である。
because each is more or less willing and more or less able to lead an English lesson to begin with.
各担任が多かれ少なかれ、英語の授業を指導する意欲と能力が っているのである。
Also, if one person takes responsibility for leading a lesson and another takes responsibility for helping students follow,
また、一人がレッスンをリードし、もう一人が生徒のフォローを担当する また、一人がレッスンをリードする責任を持ち、もう一人が生徒のフォローをする責任を持つとしたら、
it's better that the homeroom teacher who knows their students and how to deal with them best...
生徒のことを一番よく知っている担任が 生徒のことを一番よく知っている担任の方がいい。
who's able to guide and encourage them in their native language be the one helping the students follow along.
母国語で生徒を指導し、励ますことができる教師が 生徒を指導し、励ますことができる。
Finally, it depends on familiarity with teaching resources.
最後に、教材への慣れにもよる。
All students have a Chromebook they can use.
全生徒が使えるChromebookを持っています。
The level at which they are put to use in class varies by the school grade and teacher.
授業で活用されるレベルは 学年や教師によって異なります。
Third and fourth grade classes use the "Let's Try" series of textbooks.
3年生と4年生のクラスでは "Let'sTry "シリーズの教科書を使用している。
These books were introduced in 2011 and are published by Hyogo prefecture.
この教科書は2011年に導入され 兵庫県が発行している。
Fifth and sixth grade classes
小学5年生と6年生のクラス
use the "New Horizon" series of textbooks.
教科書は「ニュー・ホライズン」シリーズを使用。
These books are more current and have recently been updated.
こちらの教科書の方が最新のものです。
The curriculum for teaching English to children at the beginner level will basically be the same regardless of
子供たちに英語を教えるカリキュラムは 初級レベルの子供たちに英語を教えるカリキュラムは、基本的にどの学校でも同じです。
which book is used but the activities, media resources and supplementary materials will vary.
どの本を使っても基本的には同じですが、アクティビティやメディア教材 と副教材は異なります。
The shortcomings of any textbook may include...
教科書の欠点には...
Target language that is outdated, not useful or simply incorrect.
ターゲット言語が古かったり、役に立たなかったり、単に間違っていたりする。
Activities that are
活動内容
confusing, difficult or just not fun.
混乱する、難しい、楽しくない。
Illustrations and media that may be outdated or irrelevant.
時代遅れのイラストやメディア。
And...
そして...
inability to facilitate activities when textbooks go missing.
教科書がなくなると、活動を円滑に進めることができない。
Students can look at each other's textbooks, but they can't write in them.
生徒がお互いの教科書を見ることはできる、 教科書に書き込むことはできない。
Teachers have to be able to accommodate students who don't have their textbook or they will be left out of
教師は教科書を持っていない生徒を受け入れなければならない。 教科書を持っていない生徒を受け入れなければならない。
many listening and writing exercise.
多くのリスニングやライティングの練習がある。
Not having the textbook also means not having the materials or cards included in the book.
教科書がないということは 教科書に載っている教材やカードがないということでもある。
Teachers will have to improvise to make sure students can participate
教師は生徒が参加できるように 生徒が参加できるように
in certain conversation activities, too
ある種の会話活動にも
Some shortcomings of the textbooks currently in use -
現在使われている教科書の欠点
specifically "Let's Try"...
特に「やってみよう」...
Numbers to 20 are covered for one month in third grade.
20までの数字は3年生で1ヶ月間習う。
Numbers to 12 are covered for one month in fourth grade.
4年生では12までの数字を1ヶ月間学びます。
This is nowhere near enough practice with numbers considering they're used for so many things like
これでは数字の練習にならない。 を使うことを考えると、これでは練習不足と言わざるを得ない。
time, dates, money, etc
時間、日付、お金など
The difference between
の違い
singular and plural nouns is also covered very briefly.
単数名詞と複数名詞の違いも簡単に説明する。
This is a very important language point in English, but it can be confusing.
これは英語では非常に重要な 英語では非常に重要な言語ポイントだが、混乱を招くこともある。
The textbook covers it so briefly that teachers may skip it entirely.
教科書では簡単に説明されているので 教師は完全に飛ばしてしまうかもしれない。
Certain activities or examples are not level-appropriate. Teachers have no choice, but to skip them entirely.
ある活動や例はレベルに合っていない。 教師はそれらを完全にスキップするしかありません。
Otherwise, only letter names are taught.
それ以外は、文字名のみを教える。
Phonetic sounds, reading and writing are barely touched on even in fourth grade.
発音や読み書きは 4年生でもほとんど触れない
On one hand teachers may feel like they're not doing their job if they don't follow the textbook closely enough.
一方では、教師は自分の仕事を全うしていないと感じるかもしれない。 教科書に忠実でなければ、教師は仕事をしていないと感じるかもしれません。
On the other hand, they may feel guilty brushing over or skipping things covered in the textbook that seem too confusing or irrelevant.
一方では、教科書に載っていることを読み飛ばしたり、教科書に載っていないことを書いたりすることに その一方で、教科書で扱われていることで、あまりにわかりにくかったり、無関係に思えたりすることを 教科書に書かれていることを読み飛ばしたりすることに罪悪感を感じるかもしれない。
And this is where ALTs have a lot to offer
そして、ALTが多くのことを提供できる場所である。
among other things.
といった具合だ。
While it's important for all students to be exposed to the same basic target language and that language should follow some logical progression,
すべての生徒が同じ基本的なターゲット言語と 同じ基本的な目標言語に触れることは重要である。 その言語はある論理的な流れに沿ったものでなければならない、
A textbook is just one tool at the teacher's disposal.
教科書は教師が自由に使える道具の一つにすぎない。
Teachers must make use of any and all tools at their disposal to facilitate the most engaging and productive lessons possible.
教師はあらゆる手段を駆使し を駆使しなければならない。 を促進させなければならない。
ALTs can help.
ALTは助けになる。
They can help provide valuable insight into authentic English usage.
本物の英語の使い方を知る貴重な洞察を与えてくれる。
They can introduce more current or more useful vocabulary and phrases.
より最新の、より有用な語彙やフレーズを紹介することができる。
They can help make the most of the textbook and all other available resources.
教科書やその他の利用可能な資料を を最大限に活用できる。
They can help develop more relevant and engaging activities or methods to make lessons more interesting and productive.
より適切で魅力的な 授業をより興味深く、生産的なものにするために を開発するのを助けることができる。
They can share interesting aspects of their culture and ask students about theirs.
自分の文化の興味深い面を共有したり、生徒の文化 自分の文化について生徒に尋ねることができる。
And of course model pronunciation.
もちろん発音のモデルにもなる。
I hope I've provided some understanding of how
どのようにして
complicated an issue teaching English and elementary schools is and how much effort it takes
小学校での英語教育がいかに複雑な問題であり 小学校での英語教育がいかに複雑な問題であり、どれほどの努力が必要なのか。
from ALTs, teachers and the Board of Education to make the most of limited class time and resources and help students get the most out of that effort.
限られた授業時間を最大限に活用するために、ALT、教師、教育委員会から 限られた授業時間と資源を最大限に活用し を最大限に活用し、生徒がその努力を最大限に発揮できるようにするためには、ALTや教師、教育委員会がどれだけの努力を必要としているかということである。
I haven't even touched on many other challenges like the language barrier between teachers and ALTs,
その他にも、教師とALとの間にある言葉の壁など 教師とALTの間にある言葉の壁などである、
differences not only in culture, but personality and students with special needs, students to get themselves stuck in the I don't speak English category and
文化の違いだけでなく、性格の違い 特別な支援を必要とする生徒、生徒が「私は話せない」という 英語は話せません」というカテゴリーにはまってしまう。
students who are very very keen to learn English until it comes to speaking.
英語を学ぶことにとても熱心な生徒 話すまでは。
There is a lot I've left out, but I've tried to be thorough.
書き残したことはたくさんありますが、徹底してみました。
constructive than critical and, although I've probably missed that mark a few times,
建設的であることを心がけてきた。 何度か、その的外れなことを言ってしまったかもしれない、
I hope anyone who's come across this has gained at least some insight and
この文章を読んでくれた人が 少なくともいくつかの洞察と
I look forward to gaining further insight myself as time goes on. Thank you!
時間が経つにつれて、私自身もさらなる洞察を得ることを楽しみにしている。ありがとう！